welcome to our together tech roundtable
where we tell you what our projects are
who we are what we've been up to
and what we could use help with
um i'll start today since i rarely start
i just do the
the intro why did i just say that i've
nobody would open up to
uh we didn't hold solution raising this
week um carrie showed up and eric
didn't until later and it was actually
perfect carrie and i
i was more in a venting mood we were
gonna be discussing humor
i was like anyway so that is how
solution raising went solution raising
is an hour long conversation we generate
solutions with
10 000 people 100 000 my focus right now
is on my own existential crisis of how
to get the mlm in the world with my
limited capacity and like which
direction to take it in
and so right now i'm focusing on the
product itself
and finding people who enjoy the product
want the product to want to build that
out um because it's easier than either
figuring it out for the community or
everyone wants it on the business
structure but not necessarily the
product
um and the community is is most of the
people that i know are going to be
with that same with the same ideal of
community that i have but at the same
time
unless it's explicitly stated it's it
there's a lot of gray area of conflict
if you're not saying that we're here for
diversity and authenticity then then
that can arise
um and that is what i've been up to the
last week because i i did do a
a presentation for the product i created
a new
slide and sent it out to kylie and
carrie
and raymond and uh i'm gonna be holding
our first six week course starting out
this tuesday where i'm gonna be with
with carrie and possibly kylie and
figure
out kind of the pre the pre to the sixth
week because that's part of it is
is the product itself is like do you
come in have you never heard of anything
and
do the product or is it people who know
what i'm up to when are there to sample
the product and help
create it so anyway that is what that
was kind of all over the place but
yeah that's also what i who i am my
eccentric crisis so
who would like to go next
i can go next uh so my main project is
converati
it is a source of uh information that
earns your trust
and it's meant to provide information on
science and news
and then the partner project wikilection
which does the same thing
provides information that earns your
trust for politics
um i've been sort of
on hold ish for the last couple of weeks
been waiting for the new version of the
prototype to come out
uh while i've been working on that i've
been working on the sort of specs for
the conference platform and in doing so
have decided that
the overall decision of development
should or the direction of development
should probably change and
focus a bit more on uh it being a
platform as opposed to
just a typical coded application um
so theoretically we might be able to
talk about that today
if nothing else comes up but that's that
would probably get fairly
technical so i'm not sure that's what
i'm up to
okay and uh i'm bentley davis um
my i got a couple projects i'm working
on one is
i'm going to say goaliebot which is a
a chatbot that builds mass agreement
across the world in theory if it works
i haven't done anything on that project
i'm really getting inspired on another
project which is a
generic rating and
reporting system that allows you to
grade everything which is also a part of
contrary
and wikilection so yeah i
want to work on building that
and putting it in other spheres i also i
think i mentioned last time i kind of
got a day job so i'm working part-time
on a startup
that's also about information processing
so it's mostly
creating digital books that also
have an interactive component to them so
you're able to get it
content uh link out to content more
conveniently
and we hope it it makes it a more
a deeper and more valuable experience
than just reading the text
and more so than the current book
systems that exist today
so we'll see if that works out
[Music]
yeah i have had some interesting
meetings this week
about the canonical debate lab which is
very close to
goaliebot um we're looking for
funding so we're doing a lot of work on
that i
just uh was in a meeting with the
founder of wysaurus
which is another debate platform so i
was introducing him
to the canonical debate group of
projects that have to do with argument
and debate mapping
and then i met a guy named doran
who has an idea for a project that helps
people
handle internal conflicts which then he
hopes
would allow people to
also handle external conflicts
better so lots of things going on but
mostly i'm moving and i'm resetting up
my studio
uh and right now my desk is in a rare
areas and
my internet's choppy so i may drop off
um so we'll see how it goes
all right you know it looks sounds like
you have the most um
you know it makes more sense for you to
be lusty you have a need for something
can you
re-explain i know i might not be able to
add to the technical part but the
difference
why you're thinking that a coded app
isn't going to work in a platform
would be right the way to first of all
good job keeping track of
the terms um so the coded app
is sort of like every page is is coded
right so like if
if um so for example the most recent
change for
wiki election the existing prototype
tracks people attracts organizations
and attracts the role that the people
have held at organizations so very
simple
the next layer was meant to track
legislation and then how people had
voted on
legislation and then there was also that
extra layer of what bentley was talking
about
where it was sort of the the ability to
add things that you could score
legislation on um right like is it good
for the
environment or bad for the environment
good for business bad for her business
that kind of thing
um and then based on how somebody voted
it would
affect that you know the same score for
the person to vote
so if you vote for something that's bad
for the environment your score gets
worse for the environment
um so that was sort of the you know
that's
where it's at right now and then the
thing that we were working on
and i think a big part of why it was
stuck was the the scoring
um but also to just the fact that like
the two were tied together
and a lot of the like i guess what i
would go object
level stuff so an object is like one
individual table in the database so like
people or organizations or
legislation those would all be objects
um and
i mean this the layouts for all those
pages will be
not the same but like the same basic
principle of your showing fields
from a record um
and there are a number of other
applications out there that allow you to
sort of you know
create objects and create you know extra
fields in those tables
and then it's easier to add them to
layouts so it's
sort of like a canvas so that you can
say here's your list of fields
here's a blank page tell us where you
want them and then you can drag out
fields
um and so that's different like that's
uh a lot of how salesforce works where
they have their own developers that go
and
develop that platform and then other
people that aren't
developers can essentially make things
on their platform right can kind of make
apps
um and add objects and fields and say
you know how they look
um and it wouldn't need to be even one
percent of what salesforce does but but
the basic idea of like you know you can
add tables add fields
add the pages as they will be linked and
then at that point
someone like me could probably go in and
just change
what would that what would be the the
meta data or like data that's not
actually data
or it could get i i guess you could say
data about data
um and so that is sort of the back end
where
if we had a coder build the platform and
then they might still need to add tables
and fields and stuff like that
but once those existed then i could just
go in there and say okay this layout
should have this field here
this field here these sections show this
and as the platform builds out we can
start to
make those same sort of changes on all
of the the pages
plus the the same thing should be used
for conferrati
and for for wiki election it's sort of
two sides of the same coin
and there will almost certainly be more
apps like
wiki election we're sort of an offshoot
of converation accessing the same
overall
data set but like with a a unique view
into it but but with the same overall
like the
way to build your how the fields appear
on the
page um you know where they're ordered
what links to what
all that type of thing does that make
sense
a lot of that was over my head but kind
of so if we put in lego terms
um you're looking like as the consumer
as the person the user
um when you were talking about building
blocks is that for um
like different websites that i'm coming
to and i don't know
how it's built or as the user am i
configuring that for my
for my page you know what i mean like is
it my facebook and i get to choose where
everything is
or is facebook its own thing and then if
i come on facebook
it has it but if they wanted to use that
same piece for
twitter and twitter wouldn't it be for
for users at least not for
the i would say even far future like
that
that's theoretically possible that's way
down the road it's more meant to sort of
split
the the quote-unquote development
responsibilities where actual
programmers would be building
the platform and somebody like me that's
technical but not a
programmer can go in there sort of you
know learn okay here's how
she designed a page right it might end
up being like so you're looking to
create
the lego blocks yes because you don't
know how to make the lego blocks you
want to put the links lego is actually a
really good example
it's like instead currently we've been
building you know a toy
and instead we're saying no no instead
let's build lego so
it's just pieces that in this case
that's where it kind of falls apart
because it's meant for the
end user to to build something in this
case it's more
the developers build the pieces they
give them to me i construct something
and then that's what i put out in the
world through you know confronti through
wikileaks etc and a part of the the
platform is also to support
like they're being different for example
domain names like
wikilection.com or conference.com it
would actually be did
different apps because they're different
views into two data
like conferrati might not have a special
section for
legislation whereas of course wiki
election would
confront would show like you know a
bunch of corporations and businesses of
all sides
but whereas wiki election would only
show like
political parties lobbying groups things
that are direct like organizations that
are directly connected to politics
but still the same overall data set and
that same thing powering it
so i know what bentley's doing with the
rating system
is more like a i'm going to bring it
back to lego like a lego construction
set
like a um wow instructions
but it's like you can build anything
with it it's kind of more
the thing that the event is talking
about is like one of those really weird
lego pieces right that you're like
it's cool you're like it might be like a
a special part of a spaceship
or something where like you couldn't
build that with just the lego pieces
and you can you know reuse it wherever
you see a spot for it
but like it kind of does have a a
specialized purpose
in this case it might actually make it a
bit easier because then you can say okay
here's that
thing that does the scoring and then you
can actually say okay here's
the different settings that you can do
here's the you know where we're actually
storing the different scoring values
here's the different sets of scores
here's
what objects we're saying are the things
that get ranked
and then here are the objects that
actually get scored so in the case of
wiki election you could say the
legislation are are the things that are
actually being like
directly scored or ranked and then
the votes will be the things that i
guess are actually
counted to help affect that in the end
and then in the very end
the the politicians are the people that
sort of get automatically scored through
that system
so we'd obviously want like some better
terms to to categorize things
but it becomes easier in in in my mind
if you can just say here's this here's
how it connects you define each of these
variables like
you know where's the score being stored
what are we counting and where is it
actually being calculated
you can specify those three things you
can use it pretty much anywhere across
the platform as long as you're following
the rules of that
and so is the idea i think with this is
how i understand it with bentley's it's
the um
it's the equipment we're working out on
it's the something that you can plug and
play in different places anywhere you
need that rating system
that's the idea that it can be more more
generic because a lot of people trying
to solve this
whereas um who is which one of these
things
is doing it like the data itself is not
repetitive
so if we put in the politicians
information
and we know who they vote if someone
else has to have that information they
don't have to you know like
his feels like it's the software that's
plug and playable or the
the thing we're working out on whereas
yours is yours looking at not having to
put in that same information every time
as well and so if i use that same widget
on my thing it has it comes with that
information yeah that's
in the fairly soon future like that
should be fairly soon into
to to the app where you can sort of
query something and say hey
i want to make you know a chrome
extension that if i'm reading news it
looks for names that we know about and
then you know shows a side panel
i would definitely like something like
that to be
to be possible now how open it is and
stuff like that i'm not sure
but definitely that's how i i i wanted
to be used
even if you know it's actually con
ferrari that ends up making
the the chrome extension um
but i do want there to be some ability
for other services to sort of you know
ask for
for certain pieces of data even if it's
just hey who's this person and what's
their score in these areas
yeah i i have a couple thoughts uh maybe
i am fading in and out i wonder maybe we
could go ahead and
stop your guys videos and see if that
clears it up a bit
otherwise i don't know if you all be
able to hear me either right yeah
um good i mean hopefully it's
it's prioritizing income you know my
outgoing data rather than the incoming
um so so yeah i mean really what you
want is you you
you're you're asking for a little bit of
functionality kind of like knack
not all of nak of course but just that
ability to kind of configure
the displays and bubble and all that
it's a kind of a no code solution
um right although in this case i
wouldn't be as attached to
like the front end that gets kind of
weird
uh being all that nice right like even
if the
the designing of the page is just like
kind of code-ish right like if it's
some sort of a document like a json file
or something i would go in there and
learn the syntax of and then i can you
know
say like here's the field here's where
where it is on the page
i i think with a little bit of training
you could do that today
totally yeah yeah i've i i do that kind
of thing at work like
it's the sort of thing where really
basic syntax you know and like using
field name stuff like that i can do that
yeah and so if we can
allow that to be sort of the the
bottleneck for
i guess kind of like the actual
translation of what's happening in the
back end to the actual
front end of here are the objects that
this app uses
here are the fields on the layout
there's probably going to be a bunch of
extra in the back end that most
people won't care about but will track
just in case
and then you know if i want to add a
field or to take a field off i can just
go edit this certain file
and then i don't have to you know ask a
developer and do this and go through a
whole bunch of stuff and go
through testing because the the testing
would mostly be at the platform level on
you know adding fields on taking fields
off do things work together
that's right we'd have to figure out
though
i guess is that are you editing
because if you want those changes to go
live then we need to get a what's called
a continuous deployment
which is doable that's all built in to
github but then we'd also have to make
sure that your changes
are merged into the developer
the test version that that radical i
would be working on which
is doable um i mean i guess
the goal is for the thing that the
that radic and possibly you would be
working on would be the platform that
would translate whatever these files are
right so like those
what what what would be the things that
would actually be in in
github and then sort of their job
like the job of the platform is to so
you know take a look at what objects are
available
take a look at sort of what app they're
at right are they at
wiki election or conference or something
else and each of those would end up
having its own sort of you know set of
files or set up
settings that they would say okay
they're at
wikilection so we're gonna go over to
this you know grouping of
settings and say things right like here
here are the top level objects right
like
there's home there's there's people
there's organizations there's
elections legislation stuff like that
so if you click it'll it'll all be a
balance
between because i mean
some of that is extremely complex and
would take a long time to develop
and i don't think that you want to that
it would be worth the time
to build that right when really you're
still i mean i guess
are you thinking that this is still a
prototype or is it a beta software
you want beta because you want users to
end up
using it oh it's a combination between
because really could be either
at this point i i guess i want to shift
because i think that the platform is
sort of a better long-term
approach and so and but but i think it's
also
if we can get the bare bones part
working and put
you know a bit more of the onus on me
then i can do part of the development
myself right yeah but unless unless it
takes us longer to build a platform than
it would for us
right which is what i think it's going
to be and also you don't need a platform
after
you get a certain level of functionality
right well that's where it's a bit
iffy because there's probably going to
end up being a bunch of different
portals sort of into the conference
ecosystem
right like they're like for right now
confronti is
kind of the name for bulky platform and
they're going to end up being this
busy probably mess of an app that's
doing you know 100
different things and so i expect that
wiki election is going to be a lot
cleaner because it's kind of got more
specific purpose and over time i kind of
expect certain things to start splitting
off of confronting right like if the
science
review part gets big and there's a lot
of pieces and it it
it it makes sense to give its own portal
i imagine that will end up happening at
some point
so my understanding from what radical is
working on
is that he made it to where the data
is stored kind of abstractly
but he hadn't gone in and changed the ui
toward displays that
so his goal was actually to get
to what you want to do for the rating
system
which is also what i need because i
remember i'm making a generic rating
system so the users need to be able to
go in and say
i want to create a legislature a
legislative
person and then i want right these are
the judge
you know these are the the categories
the attributes that i want to rate
so that was all part of the plan so what
i believe he had done
back when he showed us the demo was the
back end was flexible like that but the
front end was all hard-coded
right so my understanding is he was
making that front-end more flexible now
the thing is though is that that's only
for the rating
system part to build which is kind of a
very specific scope
so building a dynamic interface for that
is
is reasonable um some of the other pages
though i don't know we'd have to look at
i just
so yeah i mean definitely i think we
need to
talk it through and figure out where we
can do it i would i do want to caution
though that there will be
it sounds like i don't know that there
will be it sounds like there's a couple
of sections and pieces that
the workload to make those dynamic might
be
more than is worthwhile right right
okay but yeah we definitely have that
discussion but then also
i'm thinking it sounds like
much of wiki election and conferrati is
just an
implement implementation of the generic
rating system
and which which is fine i mean there's
that's
definitely an important layer of it yeah
well yeah so what i just
i guess i don't know what i mean you're
gonna have
you'd need that evidence-based i just
it might be nice to list out your
feature set and say
which features are is the rating system
and which features aren't
just so we have an idea of because you
know your
code is still going to be closed source
but my hope is that the rating system
would be open source right um so
even though it wouldn't have the data
that says here's the representative and
all the stuff or even the
the structure of a representative has
these attributes
um that would never be open sourced
um but the code that lets you represent
that would be
so it might be good if we drew some
boxes around what's the rating system
and what's not and then
uh yeah so do you have a
feature list yet um
yep it's uh it's kind of spread apart
different things and it's in there oh
it's like where it is
this one um
so it might be nice if we if we
consolidated that
in some sort of table form
and then um said which one of those
features are going to be
fulfilled in the rating system and then
also get a prioritization from you on it
which i think the rating system is still
the top
priority um
i guess i don't know a spreadsheet of
those he's like i'm looking through
the materials that i have for con
ferrari and for wiki election
and like it sort of talks about how some
of the features would be used but it
doesn't you know
call them out into a list um yeah
yeah so that'd be nice if you could put
that together and then we could schedule
a meeting
yeah for sure yeah i've been good good
going through and sort of
drawing up some of the really basic
requirements for
the platform and to your point maybe it
ends up being like a weird
hybrid platform where like i do it
really doesn't need to be a very you
know polished back end like if it's just
me editing text files
that that's fine um and if i have to
check stuff in to github i can learn how
to to do that i'm sure um at this point
it's more
just about trying to simplify the
process of you know
adding a new object and then a new page
for it like that shouldn't be a week's
long
thing that should be you know an hour
max
be like you know after the table's
already been headed and we know the the
fields and
we we know the layout that should be you
know okay here's the layout for
legislation
these fields go here okay and then
here's another section where
we're going to be listing the votes and
here are the columns to use
okay now go render that yeah and that
so i think as far as it's within the
rating system thing they'll definitely
be doable
another thing we might consider is to
uh use a content management system
for the like the home page and the
description pages
and the blog i don't know if you have a
blog on there but you probably need one
for content
marketing um yeah i mean i'm
that there will end up being a set up
for it yeah and and that's where like
each individual table kind of like or
the records need the ability to have
some amount
of rich text um and so depending i mean
it could end up being like some objects
might just be a single table that
that are just the rich text right but
i'm distinguishing between
your kind of the data and then your your
more like blogish description marketing
content
right yeah i don't think that we need to
build a content management system
into no and that's where like
and i think this is probably true for
both conferrati and
wiki election where like there's going
to be a website for it
right which is going to be on some form
of acms and there might be blogs and you
know and links up to youtube and all
that sort of thing
and then there will be the actual app
right where it's probably like
app.com or app.wikilection.com
which is where the the prototype is um
that that's how you actually access the
application but then for the media the
blogs the
the press releases that sort of thing
that goes on the website
so i generally try and
keep those on the same domain there are
ways to separate out
right yeah that's what they're
developing well app
dot i'm saying even the same sub domain
okay
and the reason for that is that google
sometimes you you'd get the same
juice or not google juice
the same seo if they're if they're
separate it
google in some instances if they're
separate sub domains
i'm not too worried about seo
i mean i don't think i ever want people
to use the system
well at a certain point it will become
so like if it actually gains traction
it'll become something like
you know wikipedia or i imdb
where google actually says okay give
this more
more credence right if somebody's
searching for an actor
go ahead and use i i am db
right and yeah they have special sort of
uh uh parsers for it and stuff but like
i don't i'm not really sure what
somebody would search for to end up on
the site except for someone's name
well yeah they'd search for a
politician's name yeah but
so but your reputation based on your
blog posts
you want that to apply to whether google
recommends you also for the
politicians
have themselves separate reputations and
then they're not combined so
they're each half as likely to be shown
up on youtube because a lot of like
the major b2b apps do it that way right
like that's how sales yeah
but that's well yeah and
they're taking a hit on their seo yeah
and they don't
likely too and they're never indexing
the app
part because that's all behind you know
very well so that's the question well
you're right right
but see your data i think you do want to
index
so yeah if it's public then it should it
should be indexed some of these stuff
might be member only and then that
wouldn't be we also have to
yeah and there's a lot of technical
issues to make sure that it's indexable
yeah um i mean the good news is google's
pretty good at indexing
javascript dynamic applications these
days but i don't trust them
so i also statically generate the data
the google index and for the most part i
expect that
as it starts being used it would start
using like you know sort of the true the
original google thing
the back linking right where people like
in twitter posts and on facebook and on
their websites and stuff would be like
hey check out this profile you know for
donald trump and then link that to the
wiki election page
you do that you know ten thousand times
and all of a sudden google's like wait
what
that's what i expect will actually end
up being the thing
so i think we do need to have you choose
a content management
system to use outside of the application
and then we also need to
and maybe even get that up and running
so that you can
do that stuff because you you don't have
anything like that right now
right a wordpress website or anything um
i mean the website for what wikilection
i think is
uh wix and so really
like i still sort of uh thinking is
going to end up being
two different sub domains at least to to
start with
um if the platform ends up you know
having some sort of integrated cms where
like
i can have a page that is proper ems
and there's a decent way to sort of show
that where it's like hey here's
the web page and all the content that i
want to show there and
a deep decent way to say on the flip
side here's all the content that you
might actually
be here for um
regardless regardless of whether on the
same
sub domain or not doesn't matter so if
you get a
it would be a headless content
management system
so you would you would go to a
completely different page into the data
and then we could serve it up on
any domain anywhere i see okay so we
just need i haven't played with
headless it might be dms
yeah so we might choose one i'm trying
to think of the one that i don't think
we need to worry about that
now because i think for now i'm going to
keep the them separate where the
the the www will be
the website and then the app will will
be the app
if the app thing and when you're saying
that you're happy using
wix as your cms or whichever right at
that point
they're completely divorced so i i if i
wanted to use wix or drupal or
um the the big one whose name i'm
forgetting
it's not coming but yeah wordpress there
we go
if it's any of those right because right
now i just had to change the sub domain
mapping for
you know app.collection.com for the
prototype
and then tr triple w i change through
wix right like i
those are two totally separate things if
i want to now change
who the web hosting is like for the
website i can do that at will and
and not affect the application so yeah
so i think the main thing
we need to do is get a list of features
in pr in prioritized order for
desirability although
we of course may move the order
depending upon the speed of development
right because if something's an easy
quick win and it provides value we can
move it up in priority
but if we if we just had it in priority
order right
yeah i can probably do like the one to
ten
priority and the work with you and uh
and radek to get
a one to ten on difficulty and then we
can make that chart showing you know hey
yeah and then there will be some things
that are core if you're like hey even if
this is easy
if we can't use it until that thing is
done then there's no point in making it
until
right right yeah and then uh and then
also to have a
flag on there or an indicator whether
they
are part of the generic rating app or if
they're if it's unique to wikilection
yeah i mean in this case i think the the
writing app it would end up being built
into
like it's sort of its native place is
this app and then we can i mean i i'm
not sure how early we want to branch it
like if we want to get it
it working and see like okay this is now
able to score you know
legislation and people and this and
here's how it's mapping here
i would certainly now let's transplant
that to open source world
and then you've got to wait i would i
got some stuff i'd like to start using
it for in a couple of weeks
right so either we're gonna
you know either i'm gonna rewrite it
from scratch
i mean for my purpose as long as as my
version works
go nuts i yeah that's what i think
so i just need time to kind of at the
point where
like i'm hoping it can be reused but
also if the whole thing like
yeah it's been frozen for way too long
now i'm i'm sort of like hey if it's not
done you know in the next
well let's say five hours just don't
worry about it
right we'll just be starting from from
scratch
yeah yeah and that's the thing is i
don't i don't want to i
you know it's a balance between i
definitely don't want to slow radic down
or if or if i help on the wiki lecture
side i don't want to slow that
development down
at all
so it may just be you know i i
i look at radix code and write something
that's compatible
and then at some point we could
integrate it back in and and use it or
whatever
um so yeah it's really kind of having
that discussion
but i think it would be helpful also
know kind of like what percentage
of wikilection is this rating app
because in my mind it's a
it's like 75 but i've probably forgotten
some features that anyone
like the like depends because
it it's definitely one of the major
things but
without the evidence system it's kind of
useless because it's just numbers
like great you say there are six why
should i believe you right um
and that's where like it's going to end
up being very integrated
with that right we're at the underlying
level the content
section and the the rating system will
be really intertwined because you're
going to be like this content is saying
this but then it's proven untrue but
then it's kind of this
and then it's yeah it's going to be
interesting to figure out what the end
score ended up being after the content
is now i also envisioned
envision the ratingsism does have some
evidence pieces in it because it's
basically underneath that i think i'm
going to have
reason score um but
one the piece that i don't think it
needs that his needs is like
you had a a rather
um high-value
advanced kind of video thing
and that right that would be the level
of detail that
that these this other system wouldn't
need
um so that i think would be kind of a
unique feature but the fact of saying
okay i i put this rating and here's a
link to the evidence that's something i
think
we'll also need in there and then that
evidence could be rated using re
reason score pros and cons and debated
right
um yeah because so so another
thing that i'm considering which might
affect like
you know if you think that doing the the
the full platform is a good idea or not
is drawing up a lot more detailed specs
and then using upwork you know and
hiring some people in india
or somewhere to sort of build the
platform
um because then you know it if it takes
you know 100 hours or 200 hours like
that's a lot more manageable and then in
the end
i would hope that there's you know some
rudimentary documentation so either they
or somebody else can pick it up
but with the end goal being that you
know adding new pages adding new objects
doing stuff stuff like that um
even if it's a bit more complex than
that is in my day job
would still be um faster in the
long run i think now i i do probably
have some time for some paid work the
problem is that i
charge two to three times even at my
lowest rates
for a product that i believe helps the
world which of course
uh wikilection falls into that category
i still cost to at least two times more
than i think you could hire a pretty
decent dev
not the lowest price dev and i'm three
times more than
kind of the average price and four times
more than
the cheapest dev which i think are more
work than they're worth
um yeah no i i i also
might be i might be twice as fast or
four times as fast
you know i had charged fewer hours just
because i know what we're doing and
everything right
so we we might want to think about
whether i am
a uh efficient use of res
funds and maybe
maybe just having me manage those
resources from yeah
that's kind of what i was planning it is
easy you know having somebody that i
know and trust
sort of help both help manage them and
help answer questions that i wouldn't be
able to right and then like
i can talk to either you or radic or
whoever and sort of have that back and
forth right like
sort of product manager architect type r
r relationship in the software world yes
we probably need to have a separate
meeting
and probably that one where we talk
about budgeting what what you feel like
you can
afford to invest um although i
i still kind of feel bad about that
because i
unless i'm not going to suggest spending
any money unless i can
see that you will get hit back
right and that might be a a a part of it
right is i can
come up sort of with the um
the documentation for what i think the
first
version should be and it's probably more
realistic to start saying beta if it
ends up being a prototype
that's fine um but kind of for it to
you know even if it starts off as a
prototype that hopefully evolves into a
beta but like i really don't expect all
of this to
you know in two or three years if it's
solid and stable and has a big user base
i don't expect there to be a lot of
correlation between the two projects if
there is great
if not that's fine too um really it's
just meant to sort of
you know prove the concept and hopefully
it'll help be somewhat agile to prove
new concepts
but then to hope you know help show
people hey here's what you'd be buying
into if you supported us on patreon or
wherever yeah and is that is that your
kind of initial um
funding model is patreon
patreon or kickstarter or something like
that right like it's really
it well the initial initial funding is
me and then after that
it goes into to cr crowdfunding
and that's the goal is to where most of
the money should should come from
like so even a prototype you could start
promoting and seeing if right yeah
i guess the basic goal is i pay for a
prototype that sort of you know
gets people interested and then that
gets people interested to start paying
in to the organization and then the
organization you know
pays to build it properly okay
well yeah then then yeah let's let's get
with reddit get your feature list and
let's
talk about how we can facilitate that
in the quickest way possible including
like you said making it to where you can
contribute
time to the project more efficiently
totally yeah and that like you know it's
it's a bit easier to sort of add new
pages and
things that i'm used to to doing right
like
that's that's and i think that i think
what radic as far as the the rating
system like we said and that's kind of
the
probably the base i think radic is
already working on making it to where
you can add an entity
and it'll create a page for it
automatically i think that's
been working on so he may be partially
down that path and maybe now that
we know that if if if
if i'm an efficient use of
financial resources then you know i can
hop in and maybe we can get this thing
moving faster
right right now do you remember what
raddick is using for the back end is i
think for the the the front end
it's firebase and i think the front ends
react okay
okay and i i've that's my most recent
technology stack
okay cool now do you know because i've
been doing a bit more research just on
the the stacks everything i read was
saying like hey for
for prototypes ruby on rails keeps
coming out
no um so what is the difference like as
far as like
the wrong thing with the the gems
i mean that's that that sounds
interesting but i don't know what
firebase you know is and sort of what
libraries it has
but like i you know did a bit of
research in
into what sort of gems are available for
root for ruben rails and there were some
very
good good sounding ones right that might
make future
parts of the prototype the the problem
well
i don't know when this when they say
ruby on rails are they saying ruby on
rails
um and then having a react or some sort
of front dinner they talk about ruby on
rails and just ruby
so when all the reading i did was
talking about using ruby on rails purely
as the back end
and then i'll you know in a in a
separate conversation
i did some research on hey what's the
the difference between ruby on rails and
react
and the general consensus of a bunch of
things i i read was
okay so they're not already they're not
comparable that rails was
the back end and react was the the well
ruby
that's my understanding ruby on rails
used to be when it was first created
generates the front end html on css and
sends it to the server so it was a
completely backend system and had no
dynam
dynamic on the front end and you had to
have a different technology so i guess
now recently
they've said uh
they've said now just use it as a back
end but
your system
doesn't have a lot of back end code and
so what
firebase is is it's a fully built
it's a fully built back end it's a
no-code back-end basically
right so i don't know why
unless you unless you have some
high-level processing on the back end
which i don't think you do
so the the modern process would be to go
basically what's serverless functions is
the
is the more thing rather than using um
c sharp or ruby on rails to have
and have a back-end server that you
didn't you'd have to scale
right so now now all you do is you have
a database that you're allowed that has
an automated
so the ruby on rails is basically
building an api to your database and
it's very fast for that
but the firebase database is an api
right so we don't need it's an extra
step to put ruby on rails
right here yeah that was the universal
thing that was sort of the con
against ruby on rails was the
performance that was like
really the only thing that they said was
like yeah the performance compared to
the other options it isn't as good
um now the part that i'm not sure about
is like for something like
firebase right if you wanted to add like
is there you know just a really easy
sort of
i mean i don't think that even ruby on
rails the term plug-and-play still
doesn't apply but i'll use it because i
don't know what
to use yeah what gyms did you hear that
you thought might be
um
okay one second there might be some
pieces of functionality
right um so i i mean they had a bunch of
things they were talking about like sort
of
data display they had a bun like for
pagination for categorization for easy
cloning records soft delete
like they have a full list of you know
here's things for in
internationalization
there's some good testing stuff i'm not
i mean
coders might be interested in some of
the stuff where they're talking about
coding style and debugging
but one of the the main things is
looking at things like um
the the member sort of creation
management backend
um at some point there are a few
features that will rely
on either accepting payments or
recurring payments
and there's like a bunch of sort of like
payment back ends where i'm quite used
to working you know
in the the payment cards industry you
know
with billing not at like the most
detailed you know
actually talking to the the gateways
but like if there's a tool that we you
know
it just says hey you need you know a
gateway in these countries you need
this information and then just plug that
information into the gym and you can
start
card processing that would be awesome
right if it were
50 hours instead of 500 hours yeah i
guess
my concern is that
all of those payment processing backends
have their own
um javascript apis
and if the ruby on rails gems is just a
back end and not a front end
then right yeah and that's i guess
one of the key things is like and this
is probably something that i guess
like somebody who works in ruby on rails
currently
would have more information on but the
article is i
what i was reading they they were sort
of talking about
using ruby on rails as the back end and
a lot of people talked about using react
as the
the front end for a ruby on rails back
end
yeah but i think those gems are probably
both fronted back and ruby rails
because i don't it wouldn't be possible
in and
are you looking at the dates of these
articles
um this one you might want to do that
because if they're over two years old or
over a year
this one was from january 2020. all
right
why don't once you gather up a few of
those uh
and shoot them my way or document them
on that spreadsheet and then we can take
a look at them because i
i didn't even know that people were
starting to use ruby on rails is just a
back end
but honestly i mean
i don't see why you do the extra work
when
firebase has a back end builds the back
end for you automatically when you build
the database so yeah
actually that's a good one second let me
go to firebase i'm going to do some
researching how people are currently
talking about firebase compared to ruby
on rails and sort of seeing
what they're saying the differences are
uh sorry i remember saying
uh feature list that's gonna end up
being a weird mess because there's gonna
be like things on the platform side and
the front end and features
and that that's fine this and then write
a list of
ruby on rails uh gems etc so those are
the things i'll work on so
kind of personally i'm going to go do
some research on the firebase versus
rails just to see what people are saying
but then for our future conversation
i'll actually list out the features in
literature
a spreadsheet you know and do some of
the basic like sort of how
important they are what i figured the
dependencies are that sort of thing
and then i'll go and make a list of the
things that came up in my ruby on rails
research that sound interesting
especially as far as
existing gems are concerned that like if
firebase or something else has an
alternative i don't care about
ruby versus not i just want like a fast
good prototype that's all i care about
yeah so ruby on rails definitely was the
most
popular prototyping tool
three years ago right but that was
before you have things like fire
where you have these dynamic back ends
um
so i like in the first article i'm
hitting they say
firebase might be less time consuming
um right and then they say ruby is
simpler
um and ruby has a better community
but it's not ruby is no longer faster to
develop in
okay do you know are like i'm wondering
if that takes into account the size of
the prototype like is there
you know because with all of the gems if
firebase doesn't have
that i wonder if it's you know sort of a
rudimentary
prototype is faster in firebase but once
you hit a certain point maybe it starts
to be faster in ruby if you're going to
be you know
using like 10 gems or like yeah at that
point it's probably worth it if you know
it if you aren't using
any gems or one or two it might end up
being faster just to you
use firebase and then do the functions
of those
but if you're going to be using 10 or
20. okay now we're in the territory of
yeah that probably is you're gonna be
saving a ton of time there
yeah i mean that's definitely possible
but
uh like when you talk about members
the firebase has a full member system
built into it right um
so i guess we'd have to look to see if
those pieces aren't already built
most stuff like that you could you could
go to javascript
um like they already have an api
to those things so
we'd have to so yeah if you get a list
of the gems i mean that that definitely
would be something to be like
oh if we use this gem we don't have to
write this whole section of the app
right
totally yeah if we can figure out what
what what those situations are
and i guess that's probably what it will
end up coming down to is like
not just here are the gems that you know
sound interesting but like
hear the gems that actively sound like
they probably should be used
um and then some like i guess that's
where it gets a bit tricky with it is it
sounds like some of the gems
um i wouldn't necessarily care about
like
you or you know another developer taking
a look at it
might say like oh yeah that would be
quite useful um
because if this it it is meant to be you
know
a somewhat long-term prototype doing
like some really basic
automated testing wouldn't hurt like you
know it's just to cut
the testing loads and i can't i can't
imagine that
that they would have a gem that would
have better testing than
what we have oh really okay because
we're just writing javascript and
there's like 50 different javascript
automated testing tools
uh you know i don't know i mean go if
you want to list a few of those that
that'd be fine yeah i'll i i i might
just end up sending you
this article first because it sort of
has that actually yeah i heard one sec
i'll put this in the
chat um
because that it's got them split into i
don't know like 15 or 20 sort of like
sections and then a bunch of gems for
each section
and some of them i don't have any skin
in that game right like their testing
coding style
debugging some of them you know kind of
get into interesting to me but not
directly but i can see that they're
important things like authentication
security deployment um
search is in there like there's a bunch
of things which you know
a big part of it is how easy to actually
implement it and do we need all of the
things that it's going to do
i understand yeah there's going to be a
lot of back and forth but
i guess a big part of this is just me
doing the research on firebase
versus rails and just seeing what people
are
are saying because if firebase is fine
then i mean then it's probably easier
just to stick with it because we're
already
there yeah but yeah part of it is i'm
also
two different languages so
uh you know i don't know if radix would
be interested in
coding that so you'd have you might have
to get a full developer set of new set
of developers
that's usually actually the the biggest
decision um on what technology to go
with is just what
your developers know right um but we can
look
and i can see if there's anything in
here i mean there
also in this article if there's anything
that
stuck out to you like you mentioned the
uh the authentication authorization
um i get the admin panel
i like from my side the active record
thing sounded it
sounded interesting partly because i
like
i'm also hoping that in using ruby
because it's sort of meant to be like
that really sort of templated you know
um plug and play back in style then i'm
hoping that some of them might either
support this natively or can kind of be
re repurposed
to be that platform to sort of say hey
use this gem
and then all you know all i'll feed it
these values
paste on some file and that now tells us
how to render the page
for people or for you know or
legislation
that kind of so yeah so like active
record is an orm
object relational mapper so that's if
you're hitting a relational database
right firebase is a document store
database uh
and the one of the reasons that our
document store databases are good is
that you don't need an orm
so it's one of those things where they
created active record
because we had relational databases but
we're not using relational databases
anymore
so you don't it's a it's a it's a whole
category so
what are the ones that you don't need
anymore because when i hear relational
database that sounds like what i
i would have in mind because a huge part
of this is how the records
relate to each other so is the content
part is that all the same features
using right but actually what you talked
about is a graph database not a
relational database
okay because the the objects relate to
each other not the tables
i'm each of those being the same thing
what's that well
so uh a
at a table you say that there's a
relationship
there's a one-to-many relationship
between well actually many many between
the legislature
from the legislators table and the
um and the
like between the legislation and
politicians there's a many too many
relationship in how they voted yeah and
so how
i've like documented that is there's
three t
tables there there's people there's
there's legislation and then there's a
joint table in the middle called i think
just
voting history that then has a look up
to both of those
right that where it's got a column for
the id of the legislation
and i call them for the idea of the
person and then it says how they voted
and anything else that we we
need to know about the vote so i mean
the same thing is done in this except
it's just two tables because you have
entity and then you have a table of
relationships between the entities
although you could do that in a
relational database how does that work
with the tables having different columns
though
that's the thing is in a in a in a
in a document database you don't have
any any object can have any number of
columns and they don't have to relate to
the other columns you don't have to have
a fine
uh defined structure to put data
in a collection together okay and the
difference between relational document
is that is that a document database is
much more flexible
okay the problem is wondering if it ends
up being like
is it as good for actually like
crunching numbers and doing calculations
and you know
when those relationships between the
records in the tables are incredibly
important
and there's going to be a lot of back
and forth number crunching
is okay but doing a dynamic query
among them is a little bit slower in
this case but that doesn't
necessarily but
document databases scale a lot better
than relational databases
so as it gets bigger the document
database gets more efficient
well it's less less efficient right
than a relational database is that like
talking sort of about having a bunch of
different pages or is that talking about
as sort of the database gets more
complex because
this is going to end up being one hell
of a database no it's not complexity
it's
it's volume of data as the volume of
data increases
the the relational databases become
and that's saying both when the number
of tables increases and the number of
records
it handles both better uh
well in in the document database you
don't have multiple tables
i mean like the the the concept
of having more tables right like if if
we were having it right there there's
realistically there probably end up
being over 100 tables when all
is said and done right like if we're
looking at just you know the people
organizations their roles there's
probably going to end up being some
stuff underlying that for the content
is going to be legislation you know like
things are going to be so
interrelated it's just going to be this
spiderweb of a database map
if it were a relational database
it depends uh mostly that's not that's
not going to
affect either the data systems right
because they're both optimized to handle
that
i mean unless you're talking about
thousands of tables that's only the time
it
gets to i don't think so but i don't
think so
and like especially not super active
tables like there might end up being you
know if they're
if there were a thousand half of them
would end up being these weird fringe
tables that like
i mean some of them like if we take into
account the metadata tables and stuff
like
that maybe but yeah so yeah you would
you would but then you'd restructure how
you designed databases you go up in the
abstraction layer so
um yeah no i you know um
all the main one the main difference is
that
is that document databases are much
faster to do an initial development than
than a relational database
right because for a relational database
i have to decide what each column has
and i have to decide what value
is in a document database i can take any
document
any javascript string and i can just
throw it in the database
okay so it cuts the development time
significantly right um scales faster but
the problem is that if you
like if you're running a query that says
um dynamic
calculations like i want to write a
query that says for all these people
that have the name begin with m and have
a legislation
that that has a rating of five
that sort of thing is faster in
relational databases
right but what you do for that when you
document databases is you pre-compute
that on the back end so if your queries
aren't as
dynamic the document database okay i
mean that part
is good because that i i do expect a lot
of those kinds of searches but they
should mostly be sort of built into
the app the apps right like for example
when you're looking at a list of
organizations in in wikilection
it's going to be a filtered list showing
organizations involved in politics
yeah so there can be some sort of a flag
there and then it's easy to say go pull
that list and then you know it's already
pre pre-calculated
yeah and then there are ways to optimize
around that if you end up needing that
so um you know yeah
okay cool that's good i think we're but
we can we can talk a little bit more
about it
um but yeah yeah no take a look thank
you thank you thank you thank you thank
you thank you thank you thank you for
having us i've got a bunch of notes here
and stuff to your research
this was very helpful we'll schedule a
meeting with me and radic sometime
sure yeah for sure all right guys i
think we noticed we are at the 10
o'clock um i forgot to mention yesterday
in our meeting that i may not be at next
week's board meeting
it depends uh i just have to go pick up
my dad from uh surgery so
depends what time that is at okay
uh other than that i will maybe see you
next week and i'll be at this next week
either way
and i will so we can say goodbye to
youtube it's weirder with the cameras
off